Guide to the Southern Blacks' Migration to Pittsburgh Oral History Project, 1973-1977 AIS.1977.46
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Interview with Joseph M., November 16, 1973 (Audio-cabinet 1, Drawer 7, Cassette 21-24)
  Joseph M. was interviewed by Peter Gottlieb for approximately 104 minutes. Joseph discusses his estimated date of birth and early memories, including how he lived with a doctor and helped his mother financially as part of his earliest work experience. Joseph talks about the seasonal migration in 1911 to New York and then his own migration to Pittsburgh, discussing his numerous mill jobs in Homestead. Joseph speaks of the 1921 Depression and how he took a job outside of the mill, later doing this again in the 1930's. He recalls his reason for migrating to northern places, his first time arriving in Pittsburgh, the length of time it took to get employed once there, the boarding house in Homestead on 12th Avenue, and the pool room "scene" for Black men in Pittsburgh. Joseph also reflects upon his marriage and new residence with his wife in Homestead. He converses about the activities he participated in, including joining the church, and about the different Black churches and organizational affiliations in Homestead. Joseph talks about the origin areas of migrants to Homestead and the Black leaders in the town. Discussions about the steel companies' welfare recreation centers also occurred, covering topics that included the center's creation, educational services, welfare function, and activities. Joseph then recalls the reason why Homestead selected Reverend Nelson and his activities on behalf of the Homestead Mill, including the transportation system and how the migrants felt about Nelson. He also talks about his time within the mill, discussing the ratio of transportation people that stayed to those who left, the old-time system, the supervisors' satisfaction with Black migrants, why migrants got the "hot and dirty" jobs, and the differences between the 1916-1918 migrants and northern Blacks. He concludes his interview by talking about the violence in Homestead, where the mill was in relation to the town pre-1936 and where Black mill workers lived, and the 1919 Homestead Strike.
- Interview with Sadie M. #1, April 9, 1976 (Audio-cabinet 1, Drawer 7, Cassette 25)
  In her interview, Sadie M. talks about her family's history in Homestead and how it was a chain migration; her grandmother kept boarders in Homestead. Sadie also gives information about the beginnings of the Second Baptist church and Reverend Morton's background, including his geographic origins, self-taught education, the decision for him to quit his mill job when called to preach at Second Baptist Church in Homestead, and his salary as reverend. Additionally, Sadie reflects upon the contributions to the reverend's living expenses, how the church owned Morton's home, and reasons why Second Baptist started. She also discusses the social distinction between members of Second Baptist and Clark Memorial, going on to say that some believed that Homestead was not big enough for two Baptist churches. She talks about relationships between Second Baptist and Morton, saying that Morton tried to get unwed couples married. The discussion turned to revivals at Second Baptist and the difference between the church activities of the day and when Morton pastored the church. She also gives the geographic origins of Second Baptist's members and talks about the "states' rally" fundraising at the church. Sadie claims that most of the members of Clark Memorial hailed from Virginia, while only the older members of Second Baptist were from the South. Sadie also discusses her mother's geographic origins. Sadie then talks about the work of the missionary circle and how Second Baptist had no aid program for southern migrants. Additionally, she talks about the transportation and work of Charles Reynolds and how Second Baptist did not draw members away from Clark Memorial.
- Interview with Sadie M. #2, May 19, 25, 1976 (Audio-cabinet 1, Drawer 7, Cassette 26)
  Sadie M. begins the interview by recounting her grandparents' birthplaces and livelihoods. She retells her early childhood memories and details her parents' upbringing. When Sadie was a young girl, her family migrated to Pittsburgh. She describes their transportation, why they chose the Pittsburgh area, and their return visits back to the south. The interview then transitions to a description of the jobs her parents held before and after migration as well as how her father's early passing impacted the family. Sadie describes the Black community in Pittsburgh and how discrimination has changed as she has gotten older. The conversation then moves to her parents' involvement in Union Baptist Church and the organizations they participated in. Sadie mentions the traditions that came from her mother that are being lost to younger generations as well as the beliefs, superstitions, and medical remedies that she inherited from her mother. In particular, Sadie focuses on the connection between dreams and prophecy and New Orleans religious influences on her mother.
- Interview with Wesley M., April 2, 5, 1976 (Audio-cabinet 1, Drawer 7, Cassette 27)
  Wesley M. was born on a farm in St. Stephens South Carolina. He was the fourth out of 13 children. Wesley describes the crops his family grew, his father's job on the railroad that covered the finances of the farm, and his brief experiences with education. When he first left the farm, he worked in a sawmill, and he articulates his reasons for leaving the farm. Then he worked in Richmond, before he migrated to Homestead where he lived in a boarding house. He explains his initial reactions to Homestead and how he got a job in the mill. He lists the roles that he had while working in the mill. Wesley details his wife's background, how they met, and how she migrated north. He then returns to discussing his job and he mentions the discrimination that Black people faced on the job. He recalls the distinctions he noticed between Northern and Southern Black people and how his migration caused his family to treat him differently. Towards the end of the interview, Wesley speaks on his experience at Second Baptist Church, how it differed from the church he grew up in, and what the membership of the church was like. During the final portion of the interview, Wesley asserts that he still views himself as a Southerner regardless of how long he has lived in the North.
- Interview with Lillyan P., November 9, 10, 1973 (Audio-cabinet 1, Drawer 7, Cassette 28)
  Lillyan P. was interviewed by Peter Gottlieb for approximately 64 minutes. During the interview, Lillyan talked about her birthplace and family, education, profession as a teacher, and marriage/information about her husband. She then talks about her husband's migration from North Carolina to Virginia and his occupations at the time of their first meeting and after their marriage. When it came time to migrate to Homestead, Lillyan's husband went first and sent for her later in 1925. Lillyan then talks about her first reactions to living in Homestead, including the housing, her husband's arrangements for her arrival, memories of her Slavic neighbors, and her daily activities inside the house. Lillyan gives a description of a Black person's position in Homestead as well. She also provides information about the organizations and affiliations that she and her husband were a part of, both inside and outside of the church. Additionally, she gives information about the storefront churches in Homestead, boarders with Powells at Dixon St., and the jobs her husband had in the mill. She goes on to list her other residences, the year they purchased their first used car, and other clubs she was associated with, like the formation of the Husband and Wives club. She provides information about the leader of the Homestead Black community and her emotional commitment to the home in Virginia up until 1949. To conclude the interview, Lillyan talks about other "Petersburg-ers" in Homestead and about Grover Nelson, who was a Homestead Mill welfare worker.
- Interview with Ed R., June 10, 1976 (Audio-cabinet 1, Drawer 7, Cassette 29 (Side 2), 30)
  Ed's interview opens with an illustration of peanut farming and the salary he made working on a farm as a child. His parents moved to Richmond, Virginia while he stayed in the country with his grandparents. He eventually joined his parents to further his education, despite his distaste for the city. Ed continues to describe his education and the jobs his parents and grandparents held. Eventually his mother moved to Pittsburgh, and he joined her. Then Ed lists off the various jobs that he worked, why he quit, and his career in the police force. Ed briefly tells the story of how he and his wife met, married, and raised their children. He also distinguishes northern and southern Black people. Then he recalls his previous addresses as well as their racial and ethnic demographics. Ed discusses why he joined New Hope Baptist Church. The interview concludes with what motivated Ed to continue his education as an adult.
- Interview with Victoria S., May 25, 1976 (Audio-cabinet 1, Drawer 7, Cassette 29 (Side 1))
  Scope and Contents
  Victoria S. discusses her roots in Louisiana and her father's German ancestry. She is the youngest of 13 siblings, though only one other survived to adulthood. Her father was an engineer in Port Arthur, Texas and her mother was a housekeeper. Victoria S. details her experiences with segregation and leaving school at an early age to take care of her family after her father's passing. She came to Pittsburgh with her husband in 1942 to have better opportunities for her children. Victoria S.'s husband was employed by Westinghouse. She was a member of the Triedstone Baptist Church and an active member of Eastern Star.
- Interview with John T., November 1, 23, 1973 (Audio-cabinet 1, Drawer 7, Cassette 31-33)
  John T. reflects on his early life, including his birth date and place, his childhood home and chores, his parents' work, and his education in Virginia, including his theological studies. John discusses his marriage, tailoring, pressing, and barbershop times in his life. He notes his migration to Pittsburgh and the reasons for leaving North Carolina and migrating to Columbus, Ohio, and then to Rankin, PA, saying that the "mills [were] shutting down, no steel". He speaks about his jobs at the Westinghouse Steel Mill, including discussions about his pay (?), where Black people worked within Westinghouse in 1920, racial discrimination in the South, and about his first residence in Braddock. He then reflects on his wife's home and date of their marriage, going on to speak about welfare workers at the Edgar Thompson Mill. John also discusses the democratic political organization in Braddock among Black people and how to get good jobs. Additionally, John mentions a period of time, 1906-1911, where he worked on a dairy farm in New Jersey and explains how he obtained the position. He then gave his impression of Braddock, the length of time between his arrival in Braddock and his wife's arrival, his second residence there, and the Black migrants and churches within the town. The comparison between Northern-born versus Southern-born Blacks also came up in conversation before he talked about his career in the church. He talks about the contributions made to the church by Westinghouse executives and remarks that he "always wanted to be independent" in relation to the congregation as his position of a pastor within the church. He concludes the interview by talking about how he helped Black people get jobs and his general services to the community.
- Interview with Lee T., May 26, 1976 (Audio-cabinet 1, Drawer 7, Cassette 7 (Side 1))
  During this interview with Lee T. there was also a third person present who Lee referred to in order to confirm the more specific details of his life. He was born in South Carolina and was raised on a farm. Lee described the kinds of crops that were grown, what sharecropping meant, how he and his siblings contributed to farm work, and the behavioral expectations for children at the time. Lee never attended school but mentions his Sunday school. He argues that formal education cannot teach morality in the same way that church programs can. He worked on his own farm in South Carolina before he migrated north. After his wife's premature passing, Lee's three children remained in the south as he provided for them. In Homestead, he joined the Second Baptist Church, and he lists the other churches he attended in the area. Lee recalls work during the Great Depression and fraternal organizations.